[Music]
hello welcome to the first video in the
inventory tutorial series if you haven't
watched episode zero i highly recommend
doing that because that's just going to
go over kind of an introduction to the
system uh demoing how it works as well
as talking about kind of the skill level
um that this tutorial is aimed at and
how you can get the access to the files
and all that sort of stuff so
if you're coming across this video and
this is the first one um i do recommend
watching episode zero but with that said
let's just get straight into uh episode
one this first video or it may be two
videos we'll see how we get on it's
actually going to cover the system part
of our inventory system the way to think
of this is
you know we've got um the code the code
version
all the one zeros this is the uh this
system and then we've also got the um
you know the ui element and it's
actually going to display our inventory
as you would expect in a game so there's
going to be an inventory screen with
different inventory slots each of these
slots will have an item in it um
and it'll have an amount of that item
which is the stack amount so we're going
to be covering this part in the first
sort of one or two videos and then once
we've got the framework for the system
set up we'll start to build on the ui
and as we need new functions um of the
system from the ui for example um
splitting a stack is something that
we'll need to do we can go back and we
can um add this to our system and expand
our system but we need a framework first
for the ui to
have just something to display in the
first place and the way the system is
going to work is there's going to be
three parts there's going to be a
inventory holder think of this as uh
you know we've got a player and then
they've got their hotbar which you could
think of as a utility belt they might
have a backpack you see a holder can
have multiple
systems and that's different to the
actual assist the inventory system
is all of this
but they we will have a class called
inventor inventory system hopefully
that's not confusing so we've got the
code system and the ui sort of
representation of this system
and then we've got a inventory holder
which is our player with a backpack and
hot bar utility belt uh this could also
be you know a chest
will hold an inventory system so the
system's going to be a container for all
of our inventory slots so you can see on
the ui representation
we've got the inventory system and then
it's made up of different slots so
system and slots kind of go hand in hand
here to talk about them so we've got the
holder which is like a player or a chest
that can have one or multiple systems
and a system is made up of one or
multiple slots so again the system
is a container for
slots and an actual slot is one of these
individual squares so you know we've got
our inventory
slot
which could have a it's a really bad
sword but it's got a sword in it and
they've got two swords in their
inventory slot
in another slot they may have a potion
and they could have five potions and
they can have as many slots as they want
um in each system and you can have
multiple systems so a chest would have a
system with say 10 slots the hot bar has
got um you know normally in a game you'd
have a hot bar across the bottom of the
screen like this
each and they'd have a number of slots
on it and the player base play press one
two three four
all the way through to zero on their
keyboard so that's ten slots so a hot
bar would have ten slots a backpack
could maybe have twenty the chest could
have
uh 15 slots in it
so each of these holders has the systems
which have the slots inside them and
hopefully this will make sense as we
start to build upon this and it's this
kind of system that allows us to have
stackable items so each slot is going to
keep track of the item it has
and the stack
size and we could define how big this
stack size can get within the sort of
items property so the item may be
flagged to have a max stack size of
uh five so our potion here say we've got
a max stack size of five and we've got
five in our inventory and then we pick
up another potion on the ground
um
we can see that this is currently at its
maximum capacity so we'll just fill the
next slot with the potion that we've
just picked up so hopefully this all
makes sense if it doesn't or you want
some more clarity let me know in the
comments below and i can do some
follow-up videos to talk about this as i
said as we actually go through the code
um hopefully this will all start to
begin to make sense so let's just jump
over into unity okay so this is just a
blank 3d project within unity you know
we could have had a 2d project it
doesn't matter which pipeline you're
using just create a new project um and
just so you know
not again not that it should matter but
i'm using unity
2020.3.22 f1 the first thing we want to
do is um
you know we we need to define what
exactly an item is uh just so we can
have
something to store in an inventory so
i'm just gonna right click and go to
create folder and i'm just gonna
and i'm just gonna call this script and
within our scripts folder i'm just gonna
make a new folder called item
scripts
i'm just gonna right click here
create c sharp script and i'm just gonna
call this uh inventory item
data i'm just going to open this up in
visual studio so the first thing to do
with our inventory item data is to get
rid of monolith behavior and we're going
to derive from scriptable object which
means we don't need these and to make
these uh visible in the inspector we
just want to
come up here and open the square
brackets and go create asset menu
uh menu name
is equal to
inventory system
forward slash
inventory item so now when we go back
over to unity uh we go i'm gonna go back
to our asset folder right click create
uh folder and i'm just gonna call this
scriptable
objects and now we can right click
create inventory system and we've got
our inventory item which i'm just going
to call test
item you can see that there's no sort of
properties on that just yet and so we
can go ahead and create those for the
inventory system um all we're gonna
really care about here is uh we need a
public
sprite for the um
items icon
and we need a
and we can define a public int for our
maximum
stack size
so for this tutorial these are going to
be the only things that we need to use
however this is going to feed into the
rest of your game presumably so um when
defining an item some other stuff you
may want is a public int
um
you know id
a public string
for the display name
uh you could have a
text area
with a description
and you know you can define whatever it
is in your
uh
game an item is
you may have an item type or a weapon
type um or armor type
you know whatever you want your
inventory item to be that's that's down
to you but
the ones that we're gonna use actually
in the inventory system is an icon so we
can see what item we've got in the
inventory and then we need a max stack
size um which as i explained will define
how many of the item an inventory slot
can actually hold it's going to make
sure that's saved and let's go back over
to our inventory system
project
and i'm going to go back to scriptable
objects and you can see that our test
item now has an id a display name
description uh a slot for an icon and a
maximum stack size
for now i'm just going to put 5 in the
maximum stack size and we'll import some
sprites later on when we need them we'll
leave id alone and but for this i'll
just say test item one
and this is a test item okay that's
great so um
i'm gonna rename that to test item one
and then we can make another inventory
system inventory item and we could say
test item two
test item two description this is
another
test item
and we can hold one of these this has
got a max stack size of one great so
we've defined what um
an inventory item
is now so now we can make a slot to
actually hold the item so let's go back
over to our scripts folder and i'm just
going to right click create um folder
and i'm going to call this one the
inventory scripts open this up and then
i'm going to right click create c-sharp
script inventory slot
again this isn't a modern behavior it's
not going to sit anywhere on this scene
um
so it doesn't need the mono behavior it
doesn't need start or update
what it does need is um
it needs to be marked as system dot
serializable so we can actually see
these in the inspector then i want to
serialize
a field again so we can see these um in
the inspector i want a private
inventory item data which is that
scriptable object we've just made and
i'm going to call this item data
and then we want a serialized field
private int called
stack size so this
this is going to keep track of how many
of the item data
we've got access to and then i'm just
going to make some public properties so
we can get this
stuff elsewhere so i'm going to say
inventory item data equals
item data not equal sorry we use this um
use this separator for the expression
body definition and then we want to do
the same for the public int um stack
size
so we can accidentally change these from
outside the script but we can get a
reference to them using the public
properties and then we need when we're
making an inventory slot uh what we do
want to do is we want to make a
constructor so we can say public
inventory slot and this is going to take
in some
source data
uh
for example test item one test time two
and sword of doom
whatever the inventory slot is going to
contain um
we can pass in a source and we can also
pass in an amount of the item if we want
to
construct it with more than one item
so item data equals source
and then we can say stack size is equal
to the amount that we've passed in
but i'm also going to want a public
inventory slot
with no parameters
it sets the item data to null
and stack size
is
stack size equal to negative one so
that's essentially null as well
and the reason we're doing this is
because if we go back over here
our bag or you know the hot bar the hot
bar has the slots on it regardless of
whether there's an item in them these
are all
slots that exist
but there's no item in there so there's
null
so i'm on my mouse now instead of my
tablet
so the item
is equal to null even though the slot's
there there's no item in it and it
doesn't have any amount in it either so
we'll set the uh amount to
minus one just so we know that that's
also null as well and we can check for
that if we need to anywhere down the
line
but these slots they they exist they're
they're made they're ready to go they're
ready to hold an item but in their
default empty state they don't have
anything in them then we can make an
inventory slot with nothing in it or we
can make one that's full of stuff and
give it an amount of that stuff and
actually what's probably better is we
may want to um clear a slot as well at
some point down the line
so we can say public void clear slot and
then we can actually do this here
and then just call clear slot from our
um
constructor and then we're not having to
write this code out again because we
probably want to be able to empty out a
slot for example if we if we delete an
item we can just clear this slot instead
of creating a new slot and replacing
replacing them we can just set this slot
back to empty and then um what we want
to do is we can make two methods here so
we can say public bull
add to stack
i'm going to say int amount
and then we can just say stack size
plus equals
amount
and public void
remove
from
stack
and we can pass in an amount as well
and this will be stack size
minus equals
the amount that we're passing in and
before we add to the stack it's probably
good if we have um
a method that checks whether there is
actually room left in the in the stack
and if there's not going to be enough
room in the stack for the amount that we
want to pass in and then let us know how
much room is actually left in the stack
we can just make two more methods here
so we can do a public bull
room left in stack
which will take in the amount to add
and it'll pass back out the int
amount remaining
i'm going to make another version of
this method that just takes in the
the amount to add because we may not
always need to know how much is
remaining
and so we can just do public ball
room left in stack and make sure these
are named the same
and this will just take in an amount to
add
so we'll do this one first so we can say
if
stack size
plus the amount to add
so if we've uh if we've picked up two of
an item we're going to pass in two on
the amount to add
so stack size plus amount to add
is less than or equal
to the item data
which again is that scriptable object
we've made the item data.max stack size
then we can just return
true if we add this amount to the stack
size then
we're not gonna encroach on the maximum
stack size so if our maximum stack size
was five we had a stack size of three
and we tried to add two to the stack
then that would equal five so that'd be
fine because the stack would be it would
have room left in the stack to add this
amount to it
so it's just going to return true
otherwise there's not enough um
room in the stack so we'll just return
false so for example if this was four
and we tried to pass in two and the
maximum stack size was five
then four plus two six
that's bigger than the maximum stack
size there's not enough room left in the
stack for this amount so for this
version we can just return
our other version of the method passing
in the amount to add but we also need to
pass back out the amount remaining and
the way we can do that is we say amount
remaining
is equal to the item data dot max stack
size
minus stack size and we'll need this
later on for splitting stacks and
combining stacks for example using this
um as an example again if the maximum
stack size was five the current stack
size was four and we were trying to add
two to it which would take it to six we
want to combine the items and leave one
item kind of on the mouse so just to
explain that from our test project if i
pick up some items here so the maximum
stack size for these hearts is five and
i've got three here and i'm going to
pick up three and i want to combine them
together
so i'm going to place two from the mouse
and leave one on the mouse so i'm going
to go up to the maximum stack size
you can see that we've added two we've
got one left we put that back down
but i can put the four on the one which
brings it to five
and that's all done through checking
the
whether there's room left in the stack
then we will work that out um later so
it's good to have these here now
but we won't use them till a little bit
later on there's one more method that
needs to go into the inventory slot
class and that's about how to split
stacks but we'll come back to that when
we actually need that one so with that
done let's go back over to unity and
we're going to create another um
script so now we've defined what exactly
a slot is and that we can clear them and
manipulate them in some way we can right
click create c-sharp script and we can
start now
working on our inventory system
as in the system that holds the slots
so again this isn't going to be a mono
behavior
so we can get rid of that and we can get
rid of the start and update
and again we want this to be system
dot serializable
and then we can do serialize field
and this is going to be a private list
of inventory slots so this is going to
hold the amount of inventory slots that
we that we want so
inventory we can just call this um
inventory slots
and then we want a private int which is
going to be our inventory size which
we're going to pass in from our holder
which will send the inspector so which
is it in inventory size
and we just want to make a public getter
for our public list of inventory slots
and i'll just call this inventory slots
and
it will return our inventory slots
actually we can get rid of the private
inventory size and what we could do is
we can do a public
int
inventory
size
and then we can pass back
our inventory
slot dot count
which should be safe to do because when
we make a new because in the constructor
when we make a new inventory system we
will be taking in a size and that'll set
up the inventory list is the very first
thing it does so that should be safe we
also need to add to using statements so
we're going to be using unity
engine dot events
we can alert whoever cares that our
inventory has changed i'm going to be
using system.link um
to do some stuff as well so we'll
include that in our using statement
so then we can make a public
inventory
system constructor which is going to
take in a size
all this is going to do is it's going to
create an inventory slot list
passing in the size that's come through
it now lists you know they can grow and
shrink but we know we're going to need
this many so we may as well just do it
now and construct the list with the size
and then we can just say for int i
equals zero i is less than
size
i plus plus
and then we can do inventory slots dot
add new inventory slot
and we're going to make an empty one
which
is going to be null and with a stack
size of -1 so that's our inventory
system done so when we create a new
inventory system we're going to pass in
the size of the system and then that's
going to make um enough inventory slots
to fill fill the system sorry i forgot
we didn't put our action in after i said
we would so we're doing a public unity
action
and we're going to pass in the slot that
changed
on inventory slot changed
this is going to be an event that fires
when we add an item to our inventory
so let's go back over to unity again and
now we can define um our inventory
holder so again
c sharp script inventory holder and i'm
just going to mark this as
system.serializable
this can be a mono behavior
okay so in our holder script we just
need to make a serialized field private
int
inventory size so we're going to set
that in the inspector
and again here we need to be using unity
engine dot
events
and this is going to come into play
later and but we're just going to make a
public static unity action
passing in an inventory system
and this is going to be on
dynamic
inventory display requested
so just ignore this for now
uh you know it kind of says what it's
going to do on the name of it
but we'll come back to that when we need
it
so as well as the event we want a
public static
we can serialize another field here and
this will be a protected
inventory system
which is going to
be called
inventory system and again i'm going to
make a public getter for this so we can
get it when we need to
from other scripts
inventory system
and this will pass our as we'll get our
so in our awake method
we can say the inventory system is equal
to a new inventory system
with our inventory
size
so other scripts are going to inherit
from this this is why this is protected
not private and by default all inventory
holders will have one inventory system
on them
for example chests will have one
inventory system on them but we're going
to make a player inventory holder which
will have
two inventory systems it'll have its
backpack and it'll have a
um but for now this will this will do
fine so we've got inventory holder um
with one inventory system
so let's just see this uh how this looks
now in the inspector so if i make um
just an empty object and we'll call this
player well we'll add we'll build up on
this um as we go along so i can add our
inventory holder script to this and i
can give it an inventory size of 10. so
our inventory system in a minute is kind
of it's zero size it's empty
but with our inventory size of 10 when i
hit play
you can see that that's created 10 slots
and each slot on our inventory
takes in an item data with a stack size
so the way this looks in our test
project if i go over to my player top
down player with inventory i've got my
player inventory we have an inventory
system here
if i just hit play
we walk over some items you can see that
now there's five items
which is represented here
with our item data which is our test
item and we can pick it up and move it
between
different slots so that's what we're
building towards that's the visual
representation of the system so that's
how that looks
obviously it's a bit boring and plain
here so the last thing to do in this
video let's just make it so our player
can actually pick something up from the
ground so i'm just going to make a
capsule underneath our player
um object that we've just made here
i'll just call this uh
graphics because it's the player kind of
graphic i'm just gonna move it up so
it's sat on the floor
i'm going to remove its capsule collider
i'm going to put the collider on our
player
where the actual player object and i'll
just make i'll put box collider not and
we'll
move this up
and make it bigger
i'm just going to right click create an
empty and i'll call this
test item one
reset the transform on this
i'm going to create
a 3d object and i'll create a
sphere
and i'll just move up move our item
i use the term item lightly here
just going to come over to our assets
folder and create a um
material and i'll just say red
just pick a nice kind of pale red color
so here's an item here's our player
so
what we need for our player to actually
pick up this is we need a mono behavior
to sit on our test item so go back over
to your item scripts folder under
scripts
i'm going to create a new c-sharp script
and i'm just going to call this um
item pickup
so in our item pickup script um
it's going to need a
sphere collider
or some sort of collider
for our player to kind of hit and
collide with
i'm just going to require component type
of sphere collider and i'm gonna do a um
public
float pickup
radius
which i'll just set to one for now we
can always change it in the inspector if
it's too much or not enough
and then it's gonna need some public um
it's gonna need some item data
to show which kind of item it's actually
representing and then um
we just need a reference to our sphere
collider called uh
let's say my collider
in an awake function let's get a
reference to our sphere collider so get
component
sphere collider
and i'm going to say my collider dot is
trigger is equal to true
my collider dot radius is equal to our
pickup radius now in our ontrigger enter
function so on trigger enter i'm going
to create a variable called um
inventory
so just var inventory
i'm going to say this is equal to other
dot transform
dot get component
and it's going to look for an inventory
holder on the things that hit it
if it finds an inventory holder
so if inventory
is not equal to null so if we could just
say if uh
what we could do is say if inventory uh
then we could just return so if there's
no inventory if this is null if it
hasn't found an inventory holder script
we'll just return out of this we don't
care about what's next
but if
inventory isn't null then we can just
say
if
inventory
dot
inventory system and we're going to want
to add it to the inventory so add to
inventory which doesn't exist we need to
define that we need to make that so if i
go back over to our inventory system.cs
file
we can just make a
public void sorry public bool
add to inventory
and this is going to take in
the item so the inventory item data and
we'll just call this uh
item to add and it's going to take in an
int which will be the um
amount to add
and for now i'm just going to directly
and i wouldn't this isn't how it's going
to work obviously um but i'm just going
to add this directly
to our
to the first
item slot in the list just so we can see
this all working
we'll set this equal to a new inventory
slot
and i'm going to pass in the item to add
and the amount to add
and then i'm just going to return
return true
this is not how we're going to be doing
it um properly we need to when we
actually do this properly we're going to
be checking whether the inventory
already contains the item and if it does
add it to the stack and if it's if the
stack's full we'll get a free slot that
isn't full
etc um but just to see this kind of work
in um i'm just botching it to kind of
overwrite that first slot
so we say add to inventory we can pass
in our item data
and we'll just say one for the amount to
add
because there's one
item in the world
with the physical representation you may
want it so for example in minecraft if
you drop 10
uh torches all 10 are represented in
that one item pickup so this could be 10
and but for me i'm just gonna have one
in the inventory there
i'm just going to destroy this object if
if i've successfully added myself to the
inventory
which is indicated by whatever we return
so in this case i'm just returning true
by default because we're overwriting the
slot
then i'm going to destroy this item
if we don't add ourselves to the
inventory we won't do anything
so we'll just come back over to our
project and then we just need to add to
test this a rigid body to our player
turn off use gravity check is kinematic
now if we
select our player uh we've got our
inventory system here we've got our test
item here we can drag our item pickup on
it and then we can say the item data
this is a test item one
put the pickup radius here
and also our sphere collider is dropped
down because we moved our sphere up
so instead i'm going to put our sphere
center and then we'll just bring up our
test item
i'm going to remove the sphere collider
from our
[Music]
3d object and actually we need to say
destroyed this dot game object as well
not just to this so if we've got a
player selected you can see the
inventory holder script there if we hit
play
so we've got 10 slots the first slots
empty if we go forward we pick up the
item it deletes from the world and we
add one of the item to our test um
inventory and we add that item to
the very first inventory slot and again
i've just hard coded that
to always go into that first slot and
overwrite it and make a new slot this
isn't how we're going to be doing it
properly the next video we're going to
search our inventory slots and see if we
can find the item that we want to pass
in and if we can we're going to add the
amount to it if we can't find it we'll
get a free slot and add it to the next
freak slot that's available
and by three slot i mean a slot with no
data in it and if it can't find a free
slot and it can't add it to an already
existing item then obviously our
inventory is full so it would return
false and then the item pickup wouldn't
destroy itself from the world
but for now i think that's quite a good
place to leave this first video
if you're watching these as they go out
the full series is currently up over on
my patreon which is patreon.com
you can also get the files for each
lesson so i'm going to export
this script as it is currently now out
as a package and all
so you can download the packages in
stages as you go and again they're all
over on patreon if you need help with
anything in this video that we've
covered uh feel free to leave a comment
below or better yet go over to the
discord which again is linked in the
description
over on the discord either me or someone
else on the discord could jump in and
try and help you
that's probably the best way to get help
other than
youtube comments because you can
actually share links to your code etc
watching these on youtube as they go out
the next video will be up in one week
but in the meantime thanks for watching
and i'll catch you in the next video bye
you